okay this is lecture 12 we've reached 12
lectures and this one is more than the
others about applications of linear
algebra and and I'll
confess when I'm giving you examples of
the null space and the row space uh I
create a little Matrix you you probably
see that I just invent that Matrix as
I'm going um and I feel a little guilty
about it because the truth is
that real linear algebra uses matrices
that come from
somewhere they're not just like randomly
invented by the instructor they come
from applications they have a definite
structure
and anybody who works with
them gets uh uses that structure uh I'll
just report like this weekend I was at a
an event with chemistry professors okay
those guys are row reducing matrices and
what matrices are they working with well
their little matrices tell them how much
of each element goes into the OR each
molecule how many molecules of each go
into a reaction and what comes out and
by row reduction they get a clearer
picture of a complicated
reaction and this weekend I'm going to
the uh to a c to a sort of birthday
party at math works so math works is out
route nine in
natic that's where mat lab is created
it's a very very successful
uh software tremendously successful and
the conference will be about how linear
algebra is used and so I feel better
today to talk
about what I think is the most important
model in applied
math and the discrete version is a graph
so can I draw a graph write down the
Matrix that's associated with it and and
that's a great source of matrices you'll
see so a graph is just so a graph to
repeat has
nodes and
edges okay and I'm going to write down
the
graph a graph so I'm just creating a
small graph here a as I mentioned last
time we would be very interested in the
graph of all uh
websites or the graph of all telephones
I mean or the graph of all people in the
world here let me take just uh maybe
nodes one
two
three well I better put in an I'll put
in that edge and maybe an edge to to a
node
four and another Edge to node four how's
that
so there's a graph with four
nodes so n will be four in my n equal
four
nodes and the Matrix will have m equal
the number there will be a row for every
Edge so I've got one two three four five
edges so that will be the number of
rows and I have
to to write Down The Matrix that I want
to I I want to study I need to give a
direction to every Edge so I know a plus
and a minus Direction so I just do that
with an arrow say from 1 to two 1 to 3 2
to 3 1 to 4 3 to 4 that just tells
me uh if if I have
current flowing on these
edges then I know whether it's to count
it as positive or negative ative
according as whether it's with the arrow
or against the arrow but I just drew
those arrows arbitrarily okay because I
I my example is going to come the the
example I'll the words that I will use
will be words like
potential potential difference currents
in other words I'm thinking of an
electrical
network but that's just one possibility
my applied math class Builds on this
example it could be a hydraulic Network
so we could be doing uh flow of water
flow of
oil uh other examples this could be a a
truck a
structure uh like the a design for a
bridge or a design for a Buckminster
Fuller uh uh uh Dome or many other
possibilities so many
so but let's take potentials and
currents as as a basic example and let
me create the Matrix that tells you
exactly what the graph tells you so now
I'll call it the incidence
Matrix incidence
Matrix okay so let me write it down and
you'll
see uh what it's proper properties are
so every row corresponds to an edge I
have five rows from five edges and let
me write down again what this graph
looks like okay the first Edge Edge
one goes from node one to two so I'm
going to put in a minus one and A+ one
in this corresponds to
Node 1 2 three and four the four
columns the five rows correspond the
first row corresponds to Edge one Edge
one leaves node one and goes into node
two and that and it doesn't touch three
and four Edge
two Edge two goes oh I haven't numbered
these edges I just figured that was
probably Edge one but I didn't say so
let me take that to be Edge one let me
take this to be Edge two let me take
this to be Edge three this is Edge
four oh I'm discovering no wait a
minute did I number that twice here's
Edge four and here's Edge five okay all
right so so Edge one as I said goes from
node one to two Edge two goes from two
to three node two to three so minus one
and one in the second and third columns
Edge three goes from one to
three I'm I'm tempted to stop for a
moment with those three
edges edges one two three those form
what what would we what do you call the
the little the little the subgraph
formed by edges 1 two and
three that's a loop and the number of
loops and the position of the Loops will
be crucial okay actually here's an
interesting point about loops if I look
at those rows corresponding to edges 1
two three and the and these guys made a
loop you want to tell me if I just
looked at that much of the
Matrix it would be natural for me to ask
are those rows
independent are the rows independent and
can you tell from looking at that if
they are or are not independent you see
a a relation between those three
rows yes if I add that row to that row I
get this
row so so that's like a hint here that
Loops correspond
to
dependent linearly dependent column A
linearly dependent rows okay let me
complete the incidence Matrix number
four Edge four is going from node one to
node
four and the fifth Edge is going from
node three to node
four okay there's my
Matrix it came from the five edges and
the four nodes and if I had a big
graph I'd have a big
Matrix and what questions do I ask about
matrices can I can I ask can can we
here's the review now there's a matrix
that comes from somewhere if if it was a
big graph it would be a large Matrix but
a lot of zeros right because every row
only has two nonzeros so the number of
it's a very sparse Matrix the number of
non non Zer is exactly 2 * 5 it's 2 m
every row only has two nonzeros and
that's with a lot of structure and that
my that was the point I wanted to begin
with that graphs that real graphs from
Real uh real matrices from from genuine
problems have
structure
okay we can ask and because of the
structure structure we can answer the
the main questions about matrices so
first question what about the null
space so what am I asking if I ask you
for the null space of that
Matrix I'm asking you if if I'm looking
at The Columns of the
Matrix Four columns and I'm asking you
are those
columns
independent if the columns are
independent then what's in the null
space only the zero Vector right the
null space contains tells us what
combinations of the columns it tells us
how to combine columns to get
zero can and is there anything in the in
the null space of this Matrix other than
just the zero Vector in other words are
those four
columns independent or dependent
okay that so that's that's that's our
question let me
uh I don't know if you see the
answer whether there's so so I let's see
I guess we could do it properly we could
solve ax equals
0 so let me solve ax equals 0 to find
the null
space okay what's
ax can I I put X in here in in little
letters X1 X2 X3
X4 that's it's got four columns
ax now is that Matrix times x and what
do I get for
ax if the camera can keep that matrix
multiplication there I'll put the answer
here ax equal what's the first component
of ax
can you take that first
row Min - one 1 0 0 and multiply by the
X and of course you get x2 -
X1 the second row I get x3 -
X2 from the third row I get x3 -
X1 from the fourth row I get X4 - X1 and
from the fifth row so I get X4 -
X3 and I want to know when is the thing
zero that's that's this is my equation
ax equals
z notice what that Matrix a is doing
what we we've created a
matrix that computes the differences
across every Edge the differences in
potential let me let me even begin to
this
interpretation I'm going to think of
this Vector X which is X1 X2 X3
X4 as the potentials at the
nodes so I'm introducing a word
potentials at the
nodes and now if I multiply by
a I get these these I get these five
comp components X2 - X1
Etc and what are
they they're potential differences
that's what a computes if I have
potentials at the nodes and I multiply
by a it gives me the potential
differences the differences in
potential across the
edges okay when are those differences
zero so I'm looking for the null
space of course if all the X's are zero
then I get zero that that just tells me
of course the zero vectors in the null
space but there's more in the null
space those columns are of a are
dependent right because I can find
solutions to that equation tell me tell
me the tell me the null
space
tell me one vector in the null space so
tell me an X it's got four
components and it makes that thing zero
so what's a good X to do
that 11 one one constant potential if
the potentials are
constant then all the potential
differences are zero and that X is in
the null space what else is in the null
space if if yeah let me ask you just
always uh give me a basis for the null
space a basis for the null
space will be just that that's a that's
a good that's it that's a basis for the
null space the null space is actually
onedimensional and it's the line of all
vectors through that one so there's a
basis for it and here's the whole null
space any multiple of 111 one it's the
the whole line in four-dimensional space
do you see that that's the null space so
the so the
dimension of the null space of a is
one and there's a basis for it and
there's everything that's in it good and
what what does
that
mean physically I mean what does that
mean in the application that guy in the
null space it means
that the potentials can only be
determined up to a
constant potential differences are what
make current flow that's what makes
things
happen it's these potential differences
that will make something move in the in
our Network between X2 between node two
and node
one nothing will move if all potentials
are the same if all potentials are C C C
and C then nothing will move so we're we
have this one parameter the this AR this
arbitrary constant that raises or drops
all the potentials it's like ranking
football teams whatever we have a
there's a there's a constant or looking
at
temperatures you know there's a flow of
heat from higher temperature to lower
temperature if temperatures are equal
there's no flow and therefore we can
measure temperat we can measure
temperatures by uh Celsius or or we can
start at absolute
zero and that arbitrary it's the same
arbitrary constant that that was there
in
calculus in calculus right when you took
the integral the indefinite integral
there was a plus c and you had to set a
starting point to know what that c was
so here what often happens is we fix one
of the potentials like the last one so a
typical a typical uh thing would be to
ground that
node to set its potential at
zero and if we do that if we fix that
potential so it's not unknown anymore
then that column
disappears and we have three columns and
those three columns are independent
so I'll leave the column in there but
we'll remember that grounding a node is
the way to get it
out and grounding a node is the way to
setting a node setting a potential to
zero tells us the the base for all
potentials then we can compute the
others okay but what's the now I've
talked enough to ask what the rank of
the Matrix
is what's the rank
then uh the rank of the Matrix so we
have a 5x4 matrix we've located its null
space onedimensional
how many independent columns do we have
what's the rank it's
three and the first three columns or
actually any three columns will be
independent any three potentials are
independent good variables
the fourth
potential is
not we need to set and typically we
ground that node okay rank is three rank
equals
three okay let's see do I want to ask
you about the column space the column
space is all combinations of those
columns I I could say more about it and
I
will let me go to the
null space of a
transpose because the equation a
transpose y equals 0 is probably the
most fundamental equation of Applied
Mathematics let's talk about that that
that deserves our attention a transpose
y equals
z let let me put it on
here okay
so a transpose y equal 0 so I'm now I'm
finding the null space of a
transpose oh and if I ask you its
Dimension you could tell me what it is
what's the dimension of the null space
of a
transpose we now know enough to answer
that question what's the general formula
for the dimension of the null space of a
transpose
a transpose let let me even write out a
transpose this a transpose will be n by
m right n by
m in this case it'll be 4 by
5 those columns will become rows -1 0 -1
-1
0 is now the first
row the second row of the Matrix one Min
-1 and three
zeros the third column now becomes the
third row 0 1 1 0
-1 and the fourth column becomes the
fourth
row okay good there's a transpose that
multiplies y y1 y 2 Y3 y4 and
y5
okay now you've had time to think about
this question what's the dimension of
the null space if if I said all
those
wow usually sometime during this
semester I'll drop one of these erasers
behind there that's a great moment
there's no recovery there there's
there's uh centuries of erase are back
there
okay okay what's the dimension of the
null
space give me give me the general
formula first in terms of R and M and N
this is like crucial you the are we
struggle to to decide what dimension
meant and then we figured out what it
equaled for
an M byn Matrix of rank R and the answer
was M minus r right there are m equal
five components m equal five columns of
a
transpose and R of those columns are
pivot columns because they'll have R
pivots it has rank R and M minus r are
the free ones now for a transpose so
that's 5 - 3 so that's
2 and I would like to find this null
space I know it's
Dimension now I want to find out a basis
for
it and I want to understand what this
equation is so let me say what a
transpose y actually represents why I'm
interested in that equation yeah I I'll
I'll come I'll
put it down with those old erasers and
continue this here's the great picture
of Applied Mathematics so let me
complete that there's a
matrix that I'll call C that connects
potential differences to currents so
I'll call these These are currents on
the
edges y1 Y 2 Y3 y4 and y5 those are
currents on the
edges and this relation between
current and potential difference is ohms
law this here is Ohm's
Law ohms law says that the current on an
edge is some number times the potential
drop that's and that number is the
conductance of the edge one over the
resistance this is this is the old
current is is uh resist the relation of
current resistance and change in
potential so it's a change in potential
that makes some current
happen and it's ohms law that says how
much current happens okay and then the
final step of this framework is the
equation a a transpose y =
0 and
that's what do that
saying it has a famous name it's Kirk
off's current law KCl Kirk off's current
law a transpose y equals z so that when
I'm solving when I go back up with this
Blackboard and solve a transpose y equal
0 it's it's it's this uh it's this
pattern of that that I want you to see
that we had rectangular matrices but and
real applications but in those real
applications Comes A and A transpose so
our four subspaces are exactly the right
things to know about all right let's
know about
that null space of a transpose wait a
minute where did it
go here it is okay okay null space of a
transpose we know what its Dimension
should
be let's find out tell me a vector in
it tell me now so what am I asking you
I'm asking you for five
currents that
satisfy Kirk off's current law so we you
better understand what that law says
that that law a transpose y equals 0
what does that
say uh say in the first row of a
transpose that says so the first row of
a transpose says minus y1 -
Y3 - y4 is
zero where did that equation come from
let me I'll redraw the graph can I
redraw the graph here so that we maybe
here so that we see again the the there
was node one node two node three node
four was off here that was that was our
graph we had currents on those we had a
current y1 going there we had a current
Y what were the other what are those
Edge numbers y4
here and Y3
here and then a y 2 and a
y5 I'm just copying what was on the
other board so it's convenient to see it
what is this equation telling me this
first equation of Kirk's current
law what does that mean for that
graph well I see y1 Y3 and y4 as the
currents leaving no
one so sure enough the first equation
refers to node one and what does it say
it says that the net flow is
zero that that equation a transpose y
Kirk's current law is a balance equation
a conservation law physicists be
overjoyed right by this stuff it's it
says that in equals
out and in this
case the three arrows are all going out
so it says y1 Y3 and y4 add to zero
let's take the next one the second row
is y1 minus
Y2 and that's all that's in that row and
that must have something to do with node
two and sure enough it says y1 equals y
2 current in equals current out the
third one Y 2 + Y3 - y5 = 0 that's
certainly be what's up at the third node
Y 2 coming in Y3 coming in y5 going out
has to balance and finally y4 + y5 = 0
says that at this node y4 + y5 the total
flow is zero we don't you know charge
doesn't accumulate at the nodes it
travels
around okay now give
me I come back now to the linear algebra
question what's a vector y that solves
these
equations can I figure out what the null
space is
for this Matrix a
transpose by looking at the graph I I'm
happy if I don't have to do elimination
I can do elimination we know how to do
we know how to find the null space
basis we can do elimination on this
Matrix and we'll get it into a good
reduced row Echelon form and the special
Solutions will pop right out but I would
like to even to do it without that but
let me just ask you first if I did
elimination on that on that Matrix what
would the last row
become what would the last row if I do
elimination on that Matrix the last row
of R will
be all zeros right why because the rank
is three we only going to have three
pivots and the fourth row will be all
zeros when when we eliminate so
elimination will tell us what uh what we
spotted
earlier what's the null space all the
all the information what are the
dependencies we'll we'll find those by
elimination but here in a real example
we can find them by thinking
okay again my question is what is a
solution why how could current travel
around this
network without collect
in any charge at the nodes tell me a y
okay so a
basis for the null space of a
transpose how many vectors am I looking
for two it's a two-dimensional space my
bases should have two vectors in it give
me
one one set of currents suppose let me
start it
let me start with y1 as
one okay so one unit of one amp travels
on edge one with the arrow okay then
what what is
Y2 it's one also right and of course
what you did was solve Kirk's current
law quickly in the second equation okay
now we've got one amp leaving node one
coming around to node three what shall
we do
now well what shall I take for Y3 in
other words I've got a choice but why
not make it what you
said1 so I have just sent current 1 amp
around that
Loop what shall y4 and y5 be in this
case we could take them to be zero this
satisfies
Kirk off's current
law we could check it patiently that
minus y1 minus Y3 gives zero we know y1
is Y2 the others y4 + y5 is certainly
zero any current around a loop satisfies
a satisfies the current law okay now you
know how to get another
one take current around this Loop so now
let y 3 be
one y5 be one and y4 be minus one
and so so we have the first basis Vector
sent current around that Loop the second
basis Vector sends current around that
Loop and I've and those are independent
and I've got
two solutions two vectors in the null
space of a transpose two solutions to
Kirk off's current law of course you
would say what about sending current
around the big
loop what about that Vector one for y1
one for Y2 nothing on Y3 one for y5 and
minus one for y4 what about that is that
is that in the null space of a
transpose
sure so why don't we now have a third
Vector in the
basis because it's
not independent right it's not
independent this Vector is the sum of
those two if I send current around that
and around that then on this Edge Y3
it's going to cancel out and I'll have
allog together current around the whole
the the outside Loop that's what this
one is but it's a combination of those
two
you see that I've now uh I've identified
the null space of a transpose but but
but more than that we've solved Kirk
off's current
law and understood it in terms of the
network okay so that's uh that's the
null space of a transpose I guess I
there's always one more space to ask you
about
let's see I guess I need the row space
of
a the column space of a
transpose so what's what's and what's
its Dimension yep what's the dimension
of the row space of a if I look at the
original a it had five rows how many
were
independent so we I'm I guess I'm asking
you the rank again right and the answer
is three right three independent rows
when I transpose it there's three
independent columns are those columns
independent those
three the first three columns are they
the pivot Columns of the Matrix
no those three columns are not
independent there's a in fact this tells
me a relation between them there's a
vector in the null space that says the
First Column plus the second column
equals the third column they're not
independent because they come from a
loop so the pivot columns the pivot
Columns of this Matrix will be the
first the second not the third but the
fourth one columns one two and four are
okay where are they those are the
Columns of a transpose those correspond
to edges so there's Edge
one there's Edge
two and there's Edge
four so there's a that's
like that that is a smaller graph if I
just look at the part of the graph that
I've that I've uh thick used with thick
edges
it has the same four
nodes it only has three
edges and the those edges correspond to
the independent guys and in the graph
there those three edges have
no Loop right the independent ones are
the ones that don't have a loop all the
all the dependencies came from Loops
they were the things in the null space
of a transpose if I take three pivot
columns there are no dependencies among
them and they form a graph without a
loop and I just want to ask you what's
the name for a graph without a loop so a
graph without a loop is has got not very
many
edges right I've got four nodes and it
only has three edges and if I put
another Edge in I would have a
loop so it's this graph with no loops
and it's the one where the rows of a are
independent and what's a graph called
that has no Loops it's called a tree so
a tree is the name for a graph with no
loops and just to take one last step
here using our formula for dimension
using our formula for Dimension let's
let's look
once once um at
this at this formula the
dimension of the null space of a
transpose is M minus r okay this is the
number of
Loops number of independent
Loops m is the number of
edges and what is
r what is r for our we have to remember
way back the rank came we from looking
at The Columns of our Matrix what so
what's the rank let's let just remember
rank
was you remember there was one one we
had a one-dimensional n the rank was n
minus one that's what I'm struggling to
say because there were n columns coming
from the N
nodes so it's minus the number of
nodes minus
one because of that c that one one one
one vector in the null space The Columns
were not independent there was one
dependency so we needed minus one this
is a great
formula this is like the
first shall I shall I write it slightly
differently the number of edges let let
me put let me put things on have I got
it
right number of edges is M the number is
M minus r okay so so I'm getting let me
put the number of nodes on the the other
side so the number of
nodes I'll move that to the other
side minus the number of
edges plus the number of
Loops is I have minus minus one is
one the number of nodes minus the number
of edges plus the number of Loops is one
these are like Zero Dimensional guys
they're the points on the graph the
edges are like onedimensional things
they're they connect nodes the loops are
like two-dimensional things they have
like a an area and this count works for
every graph and it's known as
Oilers
formula we see Oiler again that guy
never stopped
okay and can we just check so what am I
saying I'm saying that linear algebra
proves Oilers formula Oilers formula is
this great topology fact about any
graph okay I'll draw let me draw another
graph let me draw a graph with more
edges and
Loops let me let me put in lots of okay
I just drew a graph there so what are
the what are the quantities in that
formula how many nodes have I got looks
like
five how many edges have I got 1 2 3 4 5
7 how many Loops have I got one two
three and Oilers right I always get one
that this this formula is
uh is extremely use ful in understanding
the relation of these quantities the
number of nodes the number of edges and
the number of
Loops okay I just complete this lecture
by completing this picture this cycle so
let me come to the to the
uh so this
expresses the equations of Applied math
this let me call these potential
differences say e so e is ax that that's
the that's the equation for this step
the
currents come from the potential
differences Y is
CE the potential the currents satisfy
kof's current
law those are the equations of with no
Source terms those are the equ equations
of electrical
circuits
of many those are like the most basic
three equations applied math comes in
this
structure the only thing I haven't got
yet in the picture
is an outside source to make something
happen I could add a current Source here
I could I could add external currents
going in and out of nodes I could add
batteries in the edges those are two two
ways if I add batteries in the edges
they they come into here let me add
current sources if I add current sources
those come in
here so there's a there's where current
sources go because the f is like a
current coming from
outside so we have our edges we have our
graph and then I send 1
amp into this node and out of this node
and that gives me uh a right hand side
in Kirk's current law and can I to
complete the lecture I'm just going to
put these three equations
together so I start with X my unknown I
multiply by a that gives me the
potential differences that was our
Matrix a that the whole thing started
with I multiply by
c those are the physical constants in
Oh's law now I have y I multiply y by a
transpose and now I have F so there's
the
whole thing there's the there's the
basic equation of Applied
math coming from these three steps
in which the last step is this balance
equation there's always a balance
equation to look for these are the when
I say the most basic equations of
Applied Mathematics I should say in
equilibrium time isn't in this problem
I'm not Newton's law isn't acting here
I'm I'm looking at the at the equations
when everything is settled down how do
the currents distribute in the network
and and of course there are big codes to
solve the this this is the basic problem
of numerical linear
algebra for systems of equations because
that's how they come and my final
question what can you tell me about this
Matrix a transpose
CA or even a transpose a I'll just close
with that
question what do you know about the
Matrix a transpose
a it is
always symmetric right okay thanks so
I'll see you Wednesday for a full review
of these chapters and Friday you get to
tell me
thanks